<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hold fast a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse vpon Sunday being the xxxi. of October, Anno Domini 1624. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, late of Exon Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hold fast a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse vpon Sunday being the xxxi. of October, Anno Domini 1624. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, late of Exon Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M[athewes] and I. N[orton] for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the great south doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>With an initial blank leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16350:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HOLD FAST, A Sermon Preached at PAVLS <hi>Croſſe vpon Sunday being</hi> the XXXI. of October, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1624. <hi>By</hi> IOHN GEE, <hi>Master of</hi> Arts, late of EXON Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> and <hi>I. N.</hi> for ROBERT MYLBOVRNE, and are to be ſold at his Shop at the great South doore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16350:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16350:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, SIR ROBERT NANTON, Knight, Maſter of his <hi>Maieſties Court of Wards and</hi> Liueries, and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome in their <hi>Dedicatories</hi> employ their Pen, not ſo much to craue <hi>Patronage,</hi> as to buy and purchaſe it by large (and happily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) commendation of thoſe whoſe names and fauour they implore. How plentifull matter in this kind I might be furniſhed withall, they well know that are able to ballance your pietie, learning, and othervertues. But as <hi>Cato</hi> reſolued to haue a mean <hi>Tombe,</hi> or none at al, that it might rather be asked, why he had no <hi>Monument,</hi> then why a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous:
<pb facs="tcp:16350:3"/>ſo in my ſpeaking to &amp; of your worthy ſelfe, rather would I be asked of many, why I ſaid ſo little, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any one, why ſo much. I therefore here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelfe to your <hi>Honour,</hi> by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to that ſide onely which lyeth moſt conſpicuous &amp; opportune for my harbour, and that is the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of you as you are by his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the worthy Head, and Maſter of that honourable Court, erected for the protection of thoſe, who by reaſon of <hi>Nonage,</hi> are vnable to ſupport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt iniury. In which imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, out of your religious &amp; vertuous reſolutions, the world knows you moſt ready to do <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and yeeld <hi>Protection,</hi> as by way of Iudicature vnto <hi>Orphanes,</hi> ſo alſo in a larger extent by way of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor &amp; countenance to others that need the ſame, eſpecially in cauſe of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My poore ſelfe, though not pleading either <hi>Wardable Tenure,</hi> or <hi>Infancie</hi> of years, yet in the generall as a <hi>Churchman,</hi> and in particular, as deuoted to doe all
<pb facs="tcp:16350:3"/>the ſeruice I may for the maintenance of <hi>Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed, preſume to caſt my ſelfe as a <hi>Ward</hi> into your tuition. Firſt,
<note place="margin">Eccleſia ſemper est pupilla.</note> the Church by the Ciuil &amp; Canon Lawes, is ſaid to remaine in perpetuall pupillage, and iuſtly claimeth ſuccour and defence from men in high place, as vnable to relieue it ſelfe againſt either thoſe <hi>Corrupters</hi> that wil thruſt in with <hi>ſtrange fire,</hi> to pollute the <hi>Altar;</hi> or thoſe <hi>Spoilers,</hi> that would cut ſhort the skirts of <hi>Aarons</hi> cloathing. Then alſo for my perſonall caſe in regard of my diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to vndertake ſo high a taske, I muſt needs acknowledge my ſelfe to bee a weake Infant, <hi>Puer ſum, non poſſum loqui;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 1.4.</note> and the more liable to wrong, becauſe incompaſſed with aduerſaries exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated againſt the Truth, and mee for ſpeaking Truth.
<note place="margin">Ezck. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Bryers and thornes are with mee, and I dwell amongst Scorpions,</hi> whoſe ſtings are the ſharper bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my breaſt, becauſe I haue indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored to giue <hi>Antidotes</hi> vnto the Kings liege people, for their defence againſt
<pb facs="tcp:16350:4"/>ſuch balefull poyſon, whereof my ſelfe haue formerly had a taſte. Nor am I more by mine owne danger driuen, then by your goodneſſe drawne to caſt mine vnworthy ſelfe, and theſe my poore Labors into the boſome of your Protection. Though it bee perhaps none of my leaſt faults, that without your Honours leaue I haue intruded vpon your Patronage, yet I cannot bee ſo miſtruſtfull in ſo good a cauſe, as to feare your either repulſe, or offence.</p>
            <p>In this good hope I craue your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Pardon and Fauour, alwayes praying God, whoſe cauſe I defend, whoſe truth you aduance, to proſper your Honour in all your laudable and religious indeauours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>Nouemb. the 11, 1624.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours bounden at ſeruice to be commanded, <hi>IOHN GEE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16350:4"/>
            <head>HOLD FAST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 3.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, I come quickly, hold faſt that thou haſt, that no man take thy Crowne.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt,</hi> ſo much more <hi>Iohn the Euangeliſt</hi> was a burning and a ſhining Lampe:
<note place="margin">Iohn 13.23.</note> He was the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>whom Ieſus loued, hee lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on his Lords breaſt, è ſinu Domini imbiberat Myſteria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh.</note> from out of the boſome of his Maſter hee dranke deepe of the fountaine of heauenly wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Hee wrote his <hi>Reuelations</hi> in the latter end of his deepe age; and (as may ſeeme by the profit thence vnto Gods Church) was to that end in ſpeciall manner, and miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerued; as if the lampe of his life could not bee put out, till hee had kindled all the lampes of his Writings, to giue light to the Sanctuary of God vpon earth. The tempeſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16350:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16350:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16350:6"/>of violent death could not daſh out the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of his mortalitie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Faſciculus Temporum. Euſeb. Eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 13 <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.</note> For hee being vnder <hi>Traian</hi> put into a veſſell of ſcalding oyle, yet was not completely martyred. And vnder <hi>Domitian</hi> baniſhed into <hi>Patmos,</hi> one of the Iſlands called <hi>Cyclades,</hi> or <hi>Sporades,</hi> lying in the Weſt part of <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, and by the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea; there his life in extreame age was not conſumed amongſt the dureſſes and diſtreſſes of that baniſhment, till hee had <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his courſe,</hi> and wrote to the neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Churches the laſt <hi>Omega</hi> of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Chriſt</hi> who preſent with him in body loued him; no leſſe loued him being abſent. And therefore, as he appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> in the <hi>Mount,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 22.12. Gene. 28.11. Exod. 3.2. Ierem. 38.6. Daniel 2. Acts 10.6.</note> to <hi>Iacob</hi> in the <hi>Field,</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Midian,</hi> to <hi>Ieremiah</hi> in the <hi>Dungeon,</hi> to <hi>Daniel</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to <hi>Peter</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Simon:</hi> So in good time he doth appeare to his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Iohn</hi> in this deſert Iſle, and comfort him in his exile, with ſweet <hi>voyces,</hi> heauenly <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and moſt glorious <hi>Reuclations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt <hi>Viſion</hi> contained in the three firſt chapters of this Booke, is of <hi>ſeuen golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtickes,</hi> and <hi>ſeuen Starres,</hi> repreſenting ſeuen famous <hi>Churches,</hi> and their <hi>Angels</hi> or Biſhops in <hi>Aſia minor,</hi> to which hee was directed to write ſo many ſeuerall Epiſtles. At the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth verſe of this Chapter begins the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Myſia,</hi> and one of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Churches, to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16350:6"/>whom he choſe rather to write, then to the Churches in <hi>Iudea,</hi> to ſignifie, that now the kingdome of God was come to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the <hi>partition wall</hi> broken downe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Arke of the Couenant opened, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles were admitted and adopted into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Gods people: yet ſo, as vnder the ſeuerall eſtates of thoſe ſeuen Churches,
<note place="margin">Paraeus. Bullinger. Gorran.</note> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of learned Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) the future eſtate of other Churches is deciphered, and the doctrine therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo neerely concerneth ſucceeding times, that the concluſion of euery Epiſtle hath this generall <hi>Memento, Let him that hath an care heare what the Spirit ſaith vnto the Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt part of the Predictions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions giuen to this the ſixt in order of thoſe Churches, the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> he commendeth the <hi>patience</hi> of the <hi>Angell</hi> or Biſhop there, threatens his enemies, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him of ayd and affiſtance.</p>
            <p>In the latter part, hee firſt <hi>exhorts</hi> him to <hi>conſtancie,</hi> then recounts the <hi>rewards</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours.</p>
            <p>He exhorts him to <hi>conſtancie</hi> in the words of my Text, <hi>Behold I come quickly, hold faſt that thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He recounts the <hi>rewards</hi> of conquerors in the words immediately following my Text: <hi>Him that ouercommeth will I make a pillar in the Temple of my God, &amp; he ſhall go no more out &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16350:7"/>
            <p>Where is <hi>Praelium &amp; Proemium,</hi> a holy warre, and a rich reward. A combate to bee vndergone by him that will winne, or keepe his Crowne.</p>
            <p>The former verſe, whereof I haue made choyce, is the Chriſtian mans Caſtle, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Tower of <hi>Dauid, A thouſand Shields hang therein, and all the Targets of the ſtrong men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The force of the words lies,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">1 Exhortation</note>firſt in an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,</hi> which is as the middle and center of the verſe, <hi>Hold faſt that thou haſt;</hi> and about it theſe two <hi>Motiues</hi> twine like the <hi>Serpents</hi> about <hi>Mercuries</hi> Rod:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">2 Motiues.</note>Firſt a <hi>Promiſe</hi> by way of <hi>Prediction, Behold I come ſhortly.</hi> Secondly, a <hi>Monition</hi> by way of <hi>Caution, That no man take thy Crowne.</hi> Both theſe are ſacred trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures laid vp in the Arke.</p>
            <p>The firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>The pot of Manna,</hi> ſweet, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and comfortable, <hi>Beholde, I come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is <hi>the Rod of Aaron,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> laid vp in the ſame Arke of the Couenant, a rod of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, Premonition, and Correction, <hi>That no man take thy Crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe intertained in vs by <hi>Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond kept ſafe by <hi>Feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hope</hi> of future good and happineſſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whereto the Eare openeth, whereon the Eye is fixed with expectation, and the Heart bent with longing, when the Bridegroome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16350:7"/>vnto his Spouſe the Church this moſt welcome voice, <hi>Behold I come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Feare</hi> and awfull reuerence,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whereat the eare tingleth and the heart quaketh, and all the faculties of the inner man doe apply themſelues together for the <hi>working out of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with feare and trembling,</hi> when our <hi>Maſter, Prophet</hi> and <hi>King</hi> doth inſtruct and moue vs ſaying to euery faithfull Soule, take heede, <hi>That no man take thy Crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt we behold the Sonne of God as moſt amiable and comfortable,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> there wee view him as he is <hi>ſpecioſus prae filijs hominum, fairer then the ſons of men,</hi> and with <hi>Peter</hi> we ſay <hi>Quò ibimus,</hi> whither ſhall wee goe but to thee, <hi>for thou haſt the words of eternall life; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> I that am <hi>the way, the truth and the life,</hi> doe <hi>come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond we view him as appearing in <hi>a bright conſuming ſire,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> with <hi>a two-edged ſword comming from his mouth,</hi> with a <hi>Rod of iron</hi> in his hand, with a voice full of terrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, threatning, leaſt another <hi>take thy Crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt hee appeares as in the <hi>gentle winde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond hee ſhewes himſelfe as in <hi>the thunder?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt the voice of Chriſt is as a <hi>ſweete Cimball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond like <hi>the ſound of many waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16350:8"/>
            <p>The firſt is a motiue of <hi>Comfort,</hi> promiſing aide and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of <hi>Terrour,</hi> threatning a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation for want of perſeuerance.</p>
            <p>In the hand of this good <hi>Samaritan</hi> is ſoft <hi>Oyle,</hi> and ſharpe <hi>Wine</hi> or vinegar. A comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue and a corraſiue. Such is his method of curing, if by faire promiſes hee cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade; his manner is by threatnings to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. I begin, and intend moſt to inſiſt on the maine branch of my text, the matter princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally intended, incompaſſed, and walled in (as it were) with the other parts, the <hi>Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Hold faſt that thou haſt;</hi> where two points readily offer themſelues to be conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>Actus</hi> and <hi>Obiectum.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>1 <hi>Actus</hi> a performance, <hi>Hold faſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Obiectum,</hi> the Obiect, the matter or thing poſſeſſed, <hi>that which thou haſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Looſe no opportunitie but <hi>Hold;</hi> not ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or perfunctorily, but firme and <hi>fast;</hi> thou haſt begun well, euen ſo perſeuere, holding <hi>that which thou haſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Hold faſt.]</hi> Strong was the poiſon of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes,</hi> and ſharpe the ſword of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> in this age of the Primitiue Church: like <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in euill,</hi> they were leagued and linkt in conſpiracie againſt the Lord and <hi>his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> againſt Chriſt and his Diſciples. The one ſort being Satans Aduocates, the other his Aſſaſines; the one beſeiging the <hi>holy Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16350:8"/>without the walls by hoſtilitie; the other vndermining her within the walls by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie and Treaſon. <hi>Heretickes</hi> like the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts with Scorpion-like tailes, did not only hurt wandering and wauering Chriſtians, with the deadly ſting of their contagious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; but alſo indangered many of them who had the ſeale of God on their forheads. <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> like the great red <hi>Dragon with ſeauen heads &amp; ten hornes,</hi> neuer ceaſed to perſecute the Spouſe of Chriſt, and to make warr with her ſeede: So that by the Impoſtures of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes and Crueltie of Tyrants, ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were drawne to leaue their Hold and fall backe from the Truth. Againſt ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Combattants, theſe enemies of the Goſpell, that thus ran away from the banner of Chriſt, this good <hi>Angell of Philadelphia,</hi> had hitherunto oppoſed himſelfe. Now becauſe hee ſhould not ſinke in the midſt of his conflict; our Sauiour incourageth him and his Church with this <hi>Exhortation,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hold that thou haſt.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, thou haſt begun in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> end not in the <hi>Fleſh;</hi> as yet thou beareſt the Image of <hi>God,</hi> then faſhion not thy ſelfe according to the <hi>World;</hi> thou art yet in the <hi>Light,</hi> delight not then in the <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>Darkneſſe;</hi> thine <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> hath beene <hi>ſinceritie,</hi> then let not thine <hi>Omega</hi> be <hi>ſeuſualitie:</hi> without perſeuerance the beſt Profeſſor is but as a <hi>branch</hi> cut off
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16350:9"/>from the <hi>Vine,</hi> he can bring forth no fruit, a <hi>painted Tombe</hi> full of rotten bones, a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Fig-tree,</hi> with goodly bloſſomes. Very profitable therefore and effectuall is this Act or Performance, <hi>Hold faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſtancie and Perſeuerance are in the Scriptures principally ſet forth by foure Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphors, <hi>Ploughing, Running, Standing,</hi> and <hi>Holding.</hi> The firſt two ſignifie Action and Motion; the other Quiet and Immutability.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of the foure, our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>No man that putteth his hand to the Plough and looketh backe, is apt to the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> Luk. 9.62.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>So runne that yee may obtaine.</hi> 1 Cor. 9.</p>
            <p>For the third, the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Stand therefore and your loines girded about with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Epheſ. 6.14.</p>
            <p>For the fourth, my Text ſaith, <hi>Hold that thou haſt,</hi> that is to ſay; perſeuere in faith and righteouſneſſe, and vſe thy function without feare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holding</hi> is a naturall action and geſture of the hand and other members, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of vnderſtanding by reaſon, but euen babes and ſucklings do vſe by inſtinct; nay all liuing creatures, yea and ſome ſtupid bodies alſo, though they haue not this architect or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of the hand, yet haue they the reach and force of appetite, which as it carrieth them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16350:9"/>by way of deſire to thoſe obiects which are naturall and conuenient for them; ſo when they attaine ſuch obiects, they haue alſo the facultie of naturall retention or Holding, which by inſtinct without diſcourſe, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to continue the fruition of that which is acceptable and profitable vnto them. Hence in nature wee ſee betweene ſome ſympathiſing bodies, not only a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe when they approach, but alſo an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſion when they mutually touch. So the Iron and Load-ſtone coueting one another, doe vpon touch cleaue together and faſtly hold that mutually which they haue.</p>
            <p>Shall not Grace be as effectuall and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull as Nature, to runne to and to cleaue to that which is ordained for ſpirituall food and eſtabliſhment? Shall Vnderſtanding and Knowledge in vs be more dull, and leſſe actiue then ſtupid inſtinct in ſenſeleſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? If <hi>Lapis inanimatus</hi> a dead ſtone, can hold that which it deſireth and enioyeth. Shall not much more we that are <hi>Viui Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> (as <hi>Peter</hi> calleth vs) the <hi>liuing ſtones of</hi> Gods ſpiritual houſe,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> cleaue faſt to our foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being cemented <hi>vinculoſpiritus,</hi> by <hi>the bond of the ſpirit? Hold</hi> then firme and faſt <hi>that which thou haſt.</hi> Doe not ſell thy ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all birth-right and poſſeſsion for worldly portion with prophane <hi>Eſau;</hi> doe not looſe them by negligence and diſuſe, like thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16350:10"/>that haue Charters or priuiledges granted to them, but neuer beſtirre themſelues to vſe them, nay perhaps not to looke into them, like him that <hi>his his talent in the ground;</hi> doe not forfeit them for want of Rent and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice paiable and due to our great Land-lord, who will ſay of his planted Vineyard, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectani vuas ſedecce labruſcas, I looked for grapes but behold wild grapes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. <hi>Forſake</hi> not thy <hi>firſt loue</hi> like an Harlot; deſiſt not as <hi>Demas,</hi> make not only a faire ſhew as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> but with <hi>Paul</hi> perſeuere and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue conſtant vnto the end, <hi>though thou beare in thy body the markes of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> Gal. 6.17.</p>
            <p>It is obſeruable that in all the holy Spirits letters, ſent to thoſe ſeauen Churches in the ſecond and third Chapters of this booke, one of which is this to the <hi>Angell of Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Corona nonda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur niſi legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè certanti. Tim.</note> all the promiſes runne <hi>to perſeuerers. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi dabitur,</hi> to him that ouercommeth ſhall it be giuen; to him that holdeth and <hi>holdeth faſt. Nec paranti ad praelium nec pugnanti ad ſanguinem, multò minus tergiverſenti ad pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed vincenti ad victoria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Not to him that prepares to fight, nor to him that reſiſts for a time, much leſſe to him that ſhewes his backe in cowardiſe, but to him that ouercomes to conqueſt is the reward promiſed.</p>
            <p>And thus hauing viewed and conſidered in generall the Act and manner of Holding,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16350:10"/>
               <hi>Hold faſt:</hi> wee will now view the ſpeciall Obiect or matter about which it is to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. It is here expreſſed <hi>Notanter et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuendo,</hi> by pointing to it, <hi>quod habes, That which thou haſt.</hi> And ſo theſe words are a kinde of <hi>Index</hi> or <hi>Aſterisk</hi> to direct vs by a ſigne or marke to a thing thereby ſignified.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Monitory</hi> doth not ſo much call or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake vs to looke abroad, as to ſearch and pry narrowly at home, to reflect vpon our ſelues with a <hi>Noſce teipſum;</hi> view, and ſearch, and iudge thy ſelfe and thine owne, <hi>non alios, non aliena,</hi> not other men, not the affaires of other men. See what thou haſt of heauenly and ſpirituall poſſeſsions, and bee ſure that thou get a perpetuitie in them.</p>
            <p>This watch-word of remembrance <hi>quod habes,</hi> is like the <hi>Gnomon</hi> in the Diall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haz,</hi> which will tell how farre the <hi>Sunne is gone backe,</hi> euen to a Degree: By examining what ſpirituall benefits &amp; graces we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, what light hath ſhined vpon vs, what influence of heauenly bleſsings we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly felt: we ſhall finde whether our ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Lampes haue decayed in light by clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die eclipſe, or ſtarted backe from their regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar motion by vndue retrogradation, what hold wee haue loſt of that heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which wee haue formerly <hi>laid</hi> claime vnto. The ſtyle and phraſe of exhortation is very emphaticall to this purpoſe vſed by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16350:11"/>Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ne dilabamur,</hi> which <hi>Stephen</hi> tranſlates by way of expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Ne dilabatur nobis &amp; effluat illa ſalus,</hi> let not the words of ſaluation ſlip and runn out from vs, as water out of leaking veſſels. The graces of God in Chriſt, are called <hi>Waters flowing vnto life euerlasting, Iohn</hi> 4.14. Now wee know that the nature of water is to bee fluid and paſſable, it eaſily ſlippeth away, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the veſſell bee very ſtanch wherein it is contained: Euen ſo is it with our ſpirituall poſſeſſion, it ſlideth from vs, and is eaſily loſt, vnleſſe we bee very vigilant and carefull.</p>
            <p>But to come yet neerer to this <hi>Quod habes.</hi> As in the valewing of a mans riches, it is not enough to avouch in groſſe, that hee hath great ſtore, vnleſſe ſome ſpeciall quantities or kinds bee particularized and recited, as by Inuentory: So heere we cannot ſufficiently either value other Gods children, or try our ſelues whether or no wee bee bankerupts in grace, vnleſſe we know of <hi>what ſort</hi> this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſure is, which is thus to bee held, <hi>where had, where ſought,</hi> and <hi>where not</hi> yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>The totall of theſe precious Iewels may be reduced to two heads:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Veritas,</hi> Truth of Chriſtian doctrine.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Probitas,</hi> Sinceritie of righteouſneſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The former of theſe <hi>Theoreticall,</hi> the other <hi>Practicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16350:11"/>
            <p n="1">1 The former containing the forme of wholeſome doctrine without corruption.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The latter, the ſinceritie of Sanctitie, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, Charitie, and ſuch like, in honeſt conuerſation, without all hypocriſie or diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In the firſt kinde, ſome hold not that which they had, but fall away by Hereſie, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Superſtition, through the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their vnderſtanding, extinguiſhing or darkening the light of ſauing knowledge. Of this number the Church hath been troubled withall in all ages, Apoſtates, ſuperſtitious Idolaters, Heretikes, maintainers of the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and traditions of men, oppoſite to the truth of God. Of this ſort were the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> in the Iewiſh Church, the <hi>Arrians, Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians, Marcionites, Manichees, Eutichians, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians,</hi> and others in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the other kinde, ſome hold not that which they had, but fall away by the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their will and affections, leauing the parts of pietie towards God, righteouſneſſe towards men,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> being <hi>louers of pleaſures more then louers of God, profeſsing outwardly godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but denying inwardly the power thereof.</hi> Of this ſort are our Metaphoricall Idolaters, that worſhip the wedge of gold, and <hi>make it their god by cleaning thereto through vnſatiable couetouſneſſe;</hi> cruell oppreſſors of the poore, that grind the faces of the needle, denying
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16350:12"/>reliefe to Chriſt in his poore members, who apply onely to their purſe, <hi>Tene quod habes;</hi> luxurious men, that <hi>make their belly their god, whoſe end is their ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both ſorts of theſe hauing been inlightned with the knowledge of Gods Truth, and in ſome meaſure (at leaſt in outward perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance) hauing walked in the pathes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon honeſtie, laudable vertues, yea and Chriſtian obedience; yet haue forſaken this ſtraight path; they haue gone <hi>in the way of Cain,</hi> and <hi>haue been ſeduced in the wages of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam for reward,</hi> and <hi>peruerted in the gaineſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Core.</hi> The whole Epiſtle of <hi>Iude,</hi> and the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Peter</hi> are fit Comments to expreſſe the Character of theſe crooked degenerating Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>In conſidering this Propoſition, as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire in it ſelfe, <hi>Tene quod habes, Hold that thou haſt,</hi> wee view the large extenſion of it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe to whom it is ſpoken, to wit, to all <hi>Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 It concerneth all perſons, either
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Indiuiduall,</hi> euery ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Chriſtian.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Collectiue,</hi> or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 This Precept is ſpoken to all,
<note place="margin">Times.</note> both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Churches in all <hi>Times,</hi> during the warfare of this world; whether in time of new plantation of the Church, or ancient continuance; in the Summer of flouriſhing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16350:12"/>peace, or the Winter of bitter perſecution; in the Spring of our jolitie, when we ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice our tender yeares vnto the Almightie, or in the declining of our drooping age, when we expect like <hi>ripe ſhcaues</hi> to be brought into Gods <hi>barne;</hi> in the <hi>dayes of our youth,</hi> when wee are to <hi>remember our Creator,</hi> by holding our ſelues faſt vnto him; or in our decrepid old age, <hi>when the keepers of the houſe tremble,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.3.</note> and the ſtrong men bow themſelues, and the grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ceaſe, and thoſe that looke out of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes bee darkened:</hi> that is, <hi>per totum vitae cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum,</hi> during our whole race and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in the <hi>Meſech</hi> of this world.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Perſons</hi> whom it concernes;
<note place="margin">Perſons.</note> firſt, <hi>Individually</hi> the Spirit <hi>ſtandeth at the doore, and knocketh</hi>a t the heart of euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ringing this watchword in his eare, <hi>Tene quod habes, Hold faſt</hi> that which thou haſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. None ſo great a proficient in Chriſtes Schoole, but needs this leſſon to be inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him: none ſo raw a beginner to whom this inſtruction can bee vnſeaſonable. Thou that art but a tender <hi>Babe</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>feed on the ſincere milke of the Goſpell;</hi> and to that end forſake not <hi>vina vbera veteris &amp; noui Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> the two Pappes of the Old and New Teſtament; bee not beaten off from ſucking ſpirituall nouriſhment from them. Thou that art growen vp a ſtrong man in Chriſt, and haſt <hi>ſenſus exercitatos</hi> to diſcerne betweene
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16350:13"/>good and euill, light and darkneſſe; thou that canſt inſtruct others in the way of truth and godlineſſe,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Hold faſt</hi> thy <hi>Depoſitum, Leſt when thou preacheſt to others, thy ſelfe become a caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away.</hi> And well it is by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> called the <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of pledge, a thing committed vnto vs in truſt. For as by the law of nature, <hi>redde depoſitum,</hi> doth bind euery ſuch fiduciary, not to vſe the pledge as his owne proper goods, but to bee accountable for it, and reſtore it when it ſhall be called for; otherwiſe is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of injuſtice, and violating of the <hi>dictamen rationis,</hi> the principles of naturall reaſon: So here for the treaſure of Gods truth commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our hands, we muſt acknowledge our ſelues to bee but <hi>depoſitarij,</hi> truſted as pledge-keepers, and not as <hi>proprietarij,</hi> Lords and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of it: For we are to giue account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>in illo die,</hi> in that great day of generall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, when euery one of vs ſhall be called to a reckoning how he hath diſcharged his truſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore for the better endeering this poſſeſſion; firſt remember how thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it. Secondly, foreſee the dangerous meanes which draw thee from it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Vnde habes,</hi> from whence thou haſt it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, <hi>Quomodo non tenes,</hi> by what meanes thou doſt loſe it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whence haſt it thou?</p>
            <p n="1">1 By <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> whereby thou haſt <hi>put on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16350:13"/>Chriſt, Galat.</hi> 3.27. whereby thou art <hi>buried with Chriſt,</hi> whereby <hi>planted together to the likeneſſe of his death. Rom.</hi> 6.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2 By the <hi>Preaching of the word.</hi> When thou wert but a young twig, thou waſt ingrafted by Baptiſme vnto Ieſus Chriſt; now after thou art growen to be a ſtronger branch, thy root is watered by Gods Planters, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions <hi>diſtill vpon thee as the raine, whoſe doctrine doth drop as the dewe, or as the ſmall raine vpon the tender hearbe, and as the ſhowers vpon the graſſe.</hi> Deut. 32. <hi>Paul planting,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo watering, God giuing the increaſe;</hi> who affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Sunſhine of his grace for the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thy growth and fertilitie, and vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth in patience to expect thy fruit theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers yeares, pruning thy boughes with the rodde of chaſtiſement and affliction; nay, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending yet further, to dig and dung the hungry ſoyle about thee: but if after all this planting, watering, pruning, fatning, thou ſhalt remaine ſtill barren, and <hi>cumber the ground,</hi> euen to the hindering of other plants from thriuing, what canſt thou expect, but that the axe or hatchet of Gods iudgement ſhould ſtub thee vp by the rootes, and thou be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnquenchable fire?</p>
            <p>Secondly, the manifold dangerous meanes of looſing our <hi>Hold</hi> by, may be reduced vnto theſe three, <hi>Rapto, Furto, Dolo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>violence of Robbery,</hi> when as by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16350:14"/>ſtrong hand inuaſion is made vpon vs, to quit and forſake true Religion for feare of death and perſecution. So in the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> ſome by the violent torments of raging per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions were through humane infirmitie driuen to let goe their Hold, being not able to reſiſt <hi>ad ſanguinem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> vnto blood. Whereupon ſome did temporiſe, conforming themſelues to ſome outward actions of Idolatry; others deliuered vp the Books of holy Scripture to the Pagan perſecutors, who thence were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Traditores.</hi> Theſe (alas) did <hi>humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pati,</hi> ſhew themſelues to bee but men, not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keepe vpright the ſhip from wracke in ſuch violent and tempeſtuous ſtormes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond meanes of diſpoſſeſſing vs of our heauenly treaſure,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">2 Furto.</note>is <hi>Furto,</hi> by <hi>Stealth;</hi> that is, when either the cares or pleaſures of this life, fulneſſe, plentie, peace, politike comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with others, conforming our ſelues to our neighbours or companions, doe ſeduce vs to imbrace this preſent world, and to tread Gods truth vnder our feet: when we permit by conniuence and ſleepineſſe, the tares of corruptions to be ſowen amongſt the wheat Gods word and truth: that is, when <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the wicked one ſtealeth away the good ſeed out of our hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> and ſcattereth inſtead of it the banefull and poyſonous ſeeds of corruption, both in doctrine and manners. For ſo by Gods iudgement it commonly commeth to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16350:14"/>paſſe, that degeneration in the one, begets a corruption in the other: where no due care is of preſeruing the truth of God in ſincerity of Religion; there God ſuffereth one ſinne to become the puniſhment of another, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent lewdneſſe and impuritie of life, which then &amp; there hath greateſt dominion, where the Goſpell is bereft of free paſſage, where corrupt ſuperſtition and dotages haue thruſt out of the throne true Chriſtianitie, where the weed, and ruſt, and canker of late inuented and obtruded nouelties haue ouergrowne and almoſt eaten out the pure gold of Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Doctrine. And as this is moſt iuſt; ſo is it in it ſelfe in naturall reaſon moſt probable. We ſee by experience, that he who hath held a <hi>coard</hi> with both hands, if hee let goe the hold with one, he is the leſſe able to hold faſt with the other. The <hi>Anchor of our hope</hi> is pitcht, not below in the bottome of the Sea, but aboue in the higheſt heauens: with both hands wee hold faſt this Cable; the one ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king cloſe vnto God, by holding to his truth in <hi>Religion,</hi> the other by remaining conſtant in puritie of conuerſation. If we doe but let ſlacke one of theſe our hands; though the Angell of God, yea God himſelfe ſhould crie loud vnto vs, <hi>Tene quod habes,</hi> yet hardly ſhall wee bee able to maintaine our hold with the other.</p>
            <p>The laſt meanes of loſſe is <hi>Dolo,</hi> by <hi>Fraud,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Dolo.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16350:15"/>which is practiſed vpon vs by the Deuill, by the world, and the fleſh; by wicked and lewd company imployed as their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and this engine likewiſe worketh vpon vs in both the obiects, both of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and of <hi>Honeſtie,</hi> both <hi>in dogmaticis,</hi> in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith, as alſo <hi>in moralibus,</hi> in peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our liues to vitiouſneſſe. The deceit in this kinde is different from the former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there the Deuill gaineth ground of vs onely by <hi>Surreption,</hi> poſſeſſing our minds and affections with preſent apprehenſion and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation of pleaſure, which ſo tranſporteth vs, as that the vnderſtanding is lulled aſleepe, and conſidereth not the loſſe and danger. But in this a kinde of <hi>Compenſation</hi> is pretended by way of bargaine or exchange, and our wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſoules are poſſeſſed with an opinion of Truth and Pietie, when wee runne headlong into iniquitie or errour. Heere I ſay men are dealt withall as by Commutation, to leaue that which they haue, for another doctrine which is pretended to be better, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed nothing but counterfeit, and gilded ouer with the forged luſtre of beautie, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of outward pompes, feeding the eye, and poſſeſſing the captiuated ſenſes of the ſimple: wherein wee behold the deceitfull boldneſſe of the great enemy and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; who being as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>themſelues the ſeruants of corruption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16350:15"/>libertie to them whom they ſeduce.</hi> And this is that ſnare of the Deuill, wherein <hi>they are caught to doe his will;</hi> which as it is power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in inticing vnto morall crimes, ſo much more doth it worke vpon the weaker mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, to ſeduce them from the truth of the Goſpell, and to <hi>carry them vp and downe with euery wind of doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who, or what am I (reuerend, honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and Chriſtian Auditory) that preſume to take this taske in hand, to vtter this Text with theſe polluted lips? Can I vndertake to ſpeake the words of exhortation vnto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, who my ſelfe haue been ſo late an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and ſpectacle of Inconſtancie? Can <hi>Tene quod habes</hi> ſound well out of the mouth of him, whoſe actions haue ſpoke too loud, <hi>Emiſi, amiſi quod habui,</hi> I haue left and loſt that which I had, and ought to haue kept. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy Spectators, and iudicious Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors as I behold this day, may be as ſo many witneſſes or accuſers to ſtop my mouth, or at leaſt to open it to profeſſe, that I am vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee a Phyſician to others, who haue had moſt need to heare that voyce of <hi>Cura teipſum,</hi> Phyſician heale thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Moſt true it is, that my foot, hand, and heart haue been taken, and too long held in the <hi>Snare of the Fowler,</hi> and carried away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into <hi>Babylon;</hi> where, if I conſider mine owne demerits, I deſerued to bee held in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16350:16"/>chaines of ſpirituall captiuitie, and to be kept perpetuall priſoner in the dungeon of Error, Superſtition, and blindnes; wherein my guilt hath bin the greater, in that mine hands haue not been beaten off from this Hold by the violent force of perſecuting terrour, but haue been willingly and wilfully ſtolne away by mine owne corrupt and carnall paſſions. For which mine obliquitie and grieuous defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as formerly by penne, ſo heere by voyce, &amp; before this Congregation, I humbly craue pardon of our moſt reuerend mother the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Church of England,</hi> then alſo of the ſpirituall Fathers, theſe Churches lights and guides, the <hi>Lords Biſhops,</hi> and of my venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble brethren the reſt of the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and generally of this and all other Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, whom no doubt I haue ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized. But aboue all I implore the mercy and indulgence of my heauenly Father, that hee will vouchſafe to imbrace mee his returning <hi>Prodigall Child:</hi> giuing him all humble and hearty thankes, that hee hath reduced vnto his fold, this wandering and diſeaſed Sheepe, and to our euer bleſſed Sauiour for daigning in his mercy, to looke backe vpon mee with his gracious eye, as he did vpon his lapſed Apoſtle. It was thy mercy (Oh ſweet Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) which raiſed me out of that ſtupiditie, and made mee to haue a liuely ſenſe of thy Truth and mine owne falſhood; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16350:16"/>as thou diddeſt vpon the fall of thine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle iudge him not the leſſe fit, but the more able thereupon to eſtabliſh others, by ſaying vnto him <hi>Eu tu conuerſus confirma fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres tuos.</hi> I am therefore not diſcouraged, but the more emboldned by the ſenſe of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſeaſedneſſe to ſtirre vp others vnto conſtancy in <hi>holding</hi> that faith which they haue receiued.</p>
            <p>Thus much for this precept as it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery chriſtian ſoule, (and my ſelfe in particular) to hold his owne portion that he hath, leaſt hee bee left <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>miſerable,</hi> when as perhaps hee thinkes himſelfe <hi>rich and well clad and wanting nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (right honourable and beloued Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory) giue me leaue to inſiſt vpon that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which I take to be principally here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, namly the inculcation of this precept of conſtancy vnto the <hi>collectiue members of Chriſt,</hi> namely, <hi>particular viſible Churches and Congregations.</hi> To them the Spirit as to a great and numberleſſe Auditory preacheth this wholeſome Sermon of Perſeuerance.</p>
            <p>Thou viſible particular Church of God,
<note place="margin">Mat. 13. Pom. 13.</note> whoſoeuer thou art that haſt <hi>receiued the Word with gladneſſe, that haſt caſt away the workes of darkeneſse, and put on the armour of light;</hi> that haſt abandoned the vanities of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme, and the crooked peruerſe errours
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16350:17"/>which follow mans naturall corruption: thou that haſt ſubmitted thy neck to the gentle yoake of Chriſts Croſſe, &amp; imbraced the <hi>glad tidings of the Goſpell,</hi> and doctrine of ſincere faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> which is <hi>powerfull vnto ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth;</hi> Stand faſt in that which thou haſt receiued, ſtriue and wraſtle for that <hi>faith, quae ſemel tradita eſt ſanctis, which was once giuen to the Saints;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. v. 3.</note> looſe not by fainting orſtarting, that Crowne of Honour &amp; ſacred reputation, which thou haſt worthly got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Chriſtian Churches. Imitate thoſe holy <hi>Confeſſors</hi> and <hi>Martyrs, quorum nomina in benedictionibus,</hi> whoſe very names are bleſſed. If God call thee vnto a fiery and bloody triall, prize not this tranſitory life, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>the word of life,</hi> Gods Goſpell, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>the Lord of life,</hi> Gods only begotten Sonne, and aboue <hi>eternall life,</hi> Gods bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and free <hi>gift.
<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> Eſto fidelis, Be thou faithfull vnto the death, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee the Crowne of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou that art a <hi>fruitefull Vine,</hi> planted by Gods owne right hand, and watered with the dew of Heauen, take heed that thy branches be not torne away by the violent blaſt of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, when God ſhall be pleaſed to ſuffer ſuch tempeſts to trouble the lower region of the Ayre in this militant Church. Hath God <hi>planted</hi> thee <hi>in a fruit full hill,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.</note> fenced</hi> thee and <hi>gathered out the ſtones</hi> from thy Vineyard by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16350:17"/>Reformation; take heed that thou ſuffer not thy <hi>fence</hi> to be <hi>troden downe;</hi> be watchfull, that <hi>the enuious man</hi> doe not throw in againe thoſe ſtones by deformation. Be carefull alſo that thy boughes and limmes be <hi>not ſtollen away by night, by thoſe that creepe through the hedge into the vineyard.</hi> Take heed, that the <hi>little foxes</hi> do not <hi>vndermine thine incloſure,</hi> and purloine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy beſt fruit, when they pretend to look another way, and profeſſe onely to requeſt courteous &amp; harmleſſe harbour for a while in thy ground: but in the mean time work them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in, &amp; dig their earths, and bring in their yong cubbes thither, which will ſoone learne, not onely to climbe vp to the top of the vine, and crop the faireſt branches, but alſo ſcratch vp the root of it. Of theſe I will ſay nothing, let the Spirit ſpeake, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15.
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Take vs the foxes, the little foxes that ſpoyle the Vines, for our Vines haue tender grapes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I dwel not too long vpon Vniuerſals, giue me leaue now to deſcend vnto particular application of this precept, by diſcuſſing what kind of Church it moſt properly concernes, and who are they that fruitfully vſe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſely abuſe this wholeſome ſpirituall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, <hi>Tene quod habes, Hold that thou haſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for the <hi>hauing;</hi> The <hi>Church of Rome</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogateth vnto it ſelfe the prime poſſeſſion of this ſpirituall <hi>tenure;</hi> that they only hold it <hi>in Capite</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, in their own head
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16350:18"/>the <hi>Pope;</hi> that al other Chriſtian Churches are but vnder-tenants, as holding by deriuation of petty leaſes from this <hi>vniverſall Land-lord;</hi> that they haue an indefeaſible perpetuity ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as intailed vnto the Pope, <hi>ſibi &amp; haeredibus in perpetuum,</hi> to him &amp; his heires world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end; that other Churches haue no other <hi>Charter</hi> of it, then a <hi>Tranſcript</hi> from that <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall,</hi> and no longer can hold it, then whileſt they are conformable and ſeruiceable in Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancie of vaſſalage or villenage <hi>to the Lords of the Mannor of Rome.</hi> A vaine fond incroching forgery of vſurpation, as authenticall as the pretended donation of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and other priuiledges vnto <hi>Silueſter</hi> the Pope.</p>
            <p>To theſe we may wel ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Came the word out from you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.36.</note> or <hi>did you preach the ſame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> or <hi>were wee baptized into the name of S. Peter, or S. Paul?</hi> If <hi>Prioritie</hi> imply origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall tenure in faith, ſurely <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> muſt bee the grandmother Church.
<note place="margin">Iſai. 2.3.</note> For <hi>de Sion exiuit lex,</hi> Out of Sion ſhall goe forth the Law, and the word of the Lord from Ieruſalem.</p>
            <p>The ancient Fathers reckoned not one, but many,
<note place="margin">Tertul. de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. aduerſ. Haret.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſias matrices &amp; originales fidei,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly originall Churches, wherein the faith was planted ſeuerally by diuers Apoſtles, not by one. And therfore wherſoeuer any church can ſhew conformity vnto the Charter of the Scriptures, it may rightfully plead this <hi>Habeo</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16350:18"/>as well as any other the Church of the world.</p>
            <p>As for the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we deny not but in the primitiue and better times, it might wel ſay <hi>Habeo,</hi> I haue this pledge of Truth, &amp; <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo,</hi> I keepe it intire and ſincere: But the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Roman Church, or rather the Papall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Weſterne Church, hath long ſince left that <hi>Hold;</hi> the preſent Church there hauing little elſe but locall preſcription for propertie herein.</p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Chriſtian Romans,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> according to the inſtruction of the great Apoſtle expreſſed vnto them, were not aſhamed to hold,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> that we are <hi>iuſtified freely by grace.</hi> The preſent in <hi>Rome,</hi> or depending on <hi>Rome,</hi> imbaſeth this doctrine, by mixture of <hi>workes, preparatory, ſatisfactory,</hi> and <hi>ſuperrogatory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old <hi>Chriſtian Romans</hi> were ſo obedient vnto their Inſtructors,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as to imbrace his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, when he ſaid,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers.</hi> The now <hi>new Romaniſts</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from this yoke their Clergie and Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; nay they ſubiect the Scepter of Princes to the Popes becke.</p>
            <p>S.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. in Rom.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon the aforeſaid words of the Apoſtle, ſaid, <hi>Si Propheta, ſi Euangelista,</hi> Though thou be a Prophet, or an Euangeliſt, yet thou art a ſubiect to the higher powers. And S. <hi>Bern.
<note place="margin">Bern.</note> Qui conatur excipere tentat deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere,</hi> He that would except any, goeth about to deceiue. But the moderne Order of <hi>Ieſuits</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16350:19"/>are more learned then theſe Fathers, and more wiſe then the very Apoſtles of Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Christian Romans</hi> learned of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>How can they call on him on whom they haue not beleeued?</hi> And therefore as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued only vpon God in Chriſt: ſo in prayer they called only on him. But the preſent <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> fill their churches &amp; altars of Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; oblation with ten <hi>Saints</hi> for one <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old <hi>Romans</hi> beleeued S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> when he wrote vnto them <hi>Stipendium peccati mors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>the wages of ſinne is death.</hi> But the new <hi>Romaniſts</hi> diſtinguiſhing of ſinnes <hi>mortall</hi> and <hi>veniall,</hi> maintaine, that there be ſome ſins for which death is not due.</p>
            <p>The old <hi>Romans</hi> beleeued,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that <hi>eternall life is the gift of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> but the new, that it is due to the <hi>worth of good workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ancient <hi>Chriſtian Romans</hi> learned (no doubt) the ſame doctrine of this Apoſtle, which he taught their brethren the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>As oft as yee eat this bread, and drinke this cup, ye ſhew forth the Lords death vntill he come.</hi> But the new <hi>Romaniſts</hi> robbe vs all of the <hi>Bread</hi> by a pretended Miracle of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation;</hi> and the Laitie of the <hi>Cup</hi> by a tricke of <hi>Concomitancie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am not here to read a Lecture of the differences and degenerations of the preſent Roman Church, which are ſoundly and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully demonſtrated by the lights of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16350:19"/>Churches in their controuerſall Bookes. Only this I inferre, that of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches that I know extant this day in the World, the Roman troope, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſuperlatiue Tenents of the Ieſuites) can leaſt of all iuſtifie themſelues and ſay, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Habui quod teneo,</hi> I had it from Chriſt, that which I now <hi>hold;</hi> or <hi>Teneo quod habui,</hi> what I receiued from Chriſt and his Apoſtles I ſtill maintaine intire and incorrupt; ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of <hi>Articles</hi> added to the <hi>faith,</hi> which are not of <hi>faith,</hi> ſuch enervation and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is there of thoſe which truly belong vnto Faith. So that in obedience vnto this diuine precept of <hi>holding that which we had from Chriſt,</hi> we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not hold with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but muſt hold againſt them that withdraw vs to Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>As they <hi>hold</hi> not <hi>what</hi> &amp; <hi>where</hi> they ſhould, ſo do they peruerſely and vehemently labor, to take and maintaine <hi>hold</hi> where they ſhould not. And therefore there wants not in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> a politicke care of maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this principle, <hi>Tene quod habes,</hi> let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing goe that may be gotten by pretence of Saint <hi>Peters Keyes,</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls Sword, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Excommunications, Cruſadoes</hi> &amp; ſuch like. To this end hath beene abuſed the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of chriſtian people, and the deuotion of Chriſtian Princes, to the increaſing of the Popes ſpirituall power, and the erecting of a temporall.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16350:20"/>
            <p>Some thinke that the Sea when it gaines vpon the Land in one place, by ſwallowing vp ſome Townes and Villages, it looſeth in another; but ſure the more ſwelling waues of the Sea of Rome, wherſoeuer they incroach, cannot abide any rampire againſt ſuch inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, nor will looſe any foot of ground gotten; ſo <hi>Vniverſall Oecumenicall</hi> is <hi>the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ocean:</hi> And where Papall vſurpation hath beene once beaten out, the hunger is more ſharpe to enter againe. They that ſay <hi>Tene quod habes,</hi> will much more buſily ſweat for <hi>Redime quod habebas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No marueile then if they beſiege and ſet hotly vpon a reformed Church, whereout in former times they <hi>ſuckt no ſmall aduantage,</hi> as appeares by one Pope that well vnderſtood the commodities of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Mat. Pariſ.</note> who ſaid, <hi>Verè hertus noſter delitiarum eſt Anglia, verè puteus eſt inexhauſtus, et vbi multa abundant, de multis multa licet ſumere.</hi> Verily this <hi>England</hi> is my Paradiſe, it is a plentifull Well that cannot bee drawne dry, and where there is Gods plenty, we may take enough and ſpare not.</p>
            <p>There is a ſtrong fenced Towne in the Low Countryes,
<note place="margin">Breda.</note> which at this preſent ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth great diſtreſſe by a violent ſiege, which aſſault no doubt is the hotter in the Enemie, becauſe that Towne being the inheritance of <hi>a great Prince,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Prince of Orange.</note> was of late reſcued out of their hands. Let vs at leaſt ſo farre make this our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16350:20"/>owne caſe, as to applie this to our ſpirituall vſe, to conſider with what heat and hungry deſire the Papall faction endeauours to lay againe vpon vs that their yoake of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which we not many yeares ſince, haue by Gods bleſsing ſhaken off. And long may they vainely long to intrude againe into this Paradiſe to trample and devaſtate it, with their Superſtitions and corruptions.</p>
            <p>Yet for our better caution, that wee may claſpe our hold the faſter, let vs take view of ſome of their forces and engines, by which they would beate off our <hi>hold</hi> and maintaine their owne.</p>
            <p>I will not ſearch into thoſe vſuall engines &amp; fortifications which they ſet vp in euery cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Their Churches pretended <hi>Vnitie, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalitie, Viſibilitie, Infallibilitie;</hi> their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>Saints,</hi> of <hi>Votaries,</hi> of <hi>Miracles,</hi> and ſuch like generall Arguments. I will only touch vpon thoſe their deuices and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which more neerely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne vs in this Church and State, being their <hi>attractiues ad habendum</hi> and <hi>retentiues ad tenendum</hi> for the Roman cauſe. Of diuers of which kinde I haue made more large declaration by my Pen heretofore, not here to be repeated, but only ſome adioynder thereto to be made of ſome particulars ſince come to my notice or remembrance.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which I muſt firſt acquaint you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16350:21"/>with their <hi>planting Agents &amp; Emiſſaries</hi> for the gaining men to their partie by acquaintance and ſubtill inſinuations.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Planting A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſartes.</note> To that end there hath beene a proiect of the Ieſuites to plant their fellow-Ieſuites and other Prieſts, not only in the Suburbs (which they count well furniſhed with that ſtuffe) but in euery ſtreete within the walls of this houourable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Citie. Whereto they haue made a note of ſuch Citizens as they thought they might make vſe of to afford them houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome. One whom <hi>I</hi> wel know was ſpoken to, to helpe to procure lodgings for them in ſuch parts of <hi>London</hi> as he was acquainted in. Nor is this ſeducing office appropriated to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtickes only, but further tranſmitted to other Laicke <hi>vnder-Emiſſaries,</hi> who ſhall walke ſometimes vnder the vocation of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians,</hi> whereof one ſhall carry Popiſh Books with him to mens houſes, and ſhall tell them that two or three of them bee ſuch as haue beene ſhewne to our beſt Proteſtant Diuines in <hi>England,</hi> who haue acknowledged that that they cannot be anſwered. Another when he comes to adminiſter Phyſicke ſhall aduiſe his patient to leaue his Laicke profeſſion, and ſtudie Diuinitie, not in the petit Vniuerſities of <hi>Oxon</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> but in the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Vniuerſities of <hi>Doway, Saint Omers, Paris, Valledolid</hi> &amp;c. Another of that ſtraine ſhall be ſo nimble as when he commeth to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16350:21"/>his Patient, hee ſhall intice away his young ſchollerly ſeruant, and conuey him againſt his Maſters will priuily beyond the Seas. Nay, yet lower Sciences ſhall bee a diſguiſe for ſuch vnder-ſuborned Agents, as <hi>Teaching of Muſicke,</hi> and <hi>Dauncing;</hi> the end whereof muſt be to make their Schollers turne their heads and heeles, till they caper out of their Religion.</p>
            <p>I name none, leſt I ſhould ſeeme rather to be an accuſer in bitterneſſe againſt the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, then a moniſher in charitie and dutie to my Countrey.</p>
            <p>Their next engine is, <hi>Their working vpon the diſcontents of young Schollers,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Supplanting yong Scholars</note> and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their parts and deſerts, by bemoaning the neglect had of their worth in our Schooles and Colledges, extolling of the Diſcipline and Induſtry,
<note place="margin">Eight Engliſh Colledges in Spaine.</note> eminent Learning and reward in the Seminary Colledges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, offering them meanes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of tranſportation, with Letters Commendatory in their hand, and money in their purſes.</p>
            <p>Hereof I haue formerly giuen ſome exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, yet now will adde, how in their holding faſt yong <hi>Proſelites,</hi> they exerciſe (though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly) this precept of <hi>Tene quod habes, Hold that which thou haſt gotten;</hi> which they doe not onely by <hi>gloſing arguments,</hi> and idle books of <hi>Miracles, Viſions,</hi> and <hi>Reuelatious,</hi> by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16350:22"/>which they work vpon the mind &amp; fancy; but alſo they adde an externall meanes of ſuretie, not much vnlike that which the <hi>Iewes</hi> vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Sauiour after his Paſſion, who ſet a <hi>ſure guard about the ſepulchre,
<note place="margin">Math. 27.</note> leſt he ſhould riſe againe.</hi> So theſe when they haue hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winckt and buried any <hi>Proſelite</hi> in the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of their Superſtitions, they prouide <hi>ne reſurgat,</hi> leſt he ſhould open his eyes, and riſe vp to behold the light of the Truth. And therefore they ſet <hi>a guard</hi> vpon him, to keepe him from conuerſing or conferring with any but themſelues.</p>
            <p>I haue formerly related of a <hi>Nouice-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended-Nunne,</hi> whom after they had gotten into their clutches, they were ſo carefull ouer her, that they would not ſuffer her to ſtep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtreet, without one to watch her like a Conſtable. Whereto I adde, that ſince I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of a young <hi>Vniuerſitie Scholar,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom a brace of <hi>Ieſuites</hi> gained ground ſo farre, that he yeelded a kinde of conſent of late within this twelue-moneth, to bee tranſported by them to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Doway.</hi> To which end ſome money was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered amongſt the <hi>Romanists</hi> for his <hi>Via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum.</hi> But becauſe the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> did not thinke their motiues of Argument to pierce ſo deepely into him, that they might bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his conſtancie in that reſolution, they added thereto the ſtrong coard of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16350:22"/>detenſion, or reſtraint; and for diuers weekes till hee ſhould bee packt ouer, they kept him in their Chamber cloſe Priſoner without Bayle or Mainepriſe: Imploying of him there in tranſcribing certaine idle pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of theirs, pretended for the Preſſe, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by one of them profeſſedly againſt a <hi>worthie Knight of this Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Humph. Lynde.</note> But the young Scholar being (as it ſeemes) not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee a Recluſe, and liking better to breath a little freſh ayre, ſo ſoone as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie was offered, walked out into the ſtreetes, and meeting with ſome of his good friends, to whom hee imparted the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of his gadding beyond the ſea; was thereupon diſſwaded, and reclaimed.</p>
            <p>By which <hi>young Scholar</hi> I am likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that in his time of keeping thus rety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> Chamber, there were dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought thither great packes of <hi>Engliſh Popiſh Bookes,</hi> by ſome <hi>Traders,</hi> (perhaps not farre from this place) who make other ſhew in outward profeſſion, but are content to make Merchandiſe of Religions on both hands.</p>
            <p>As they haue their incroaching hookes to draw in thoſe that are of ripe yeares,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Theeuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way children.</note> ſo much eaſier doe they get into their power and diſpoſall, the <hi>tender Plants, and very Flower of our Engliſh Gentrie:</hi> I meane young children of either Sex, whom in their <hi>Nonage</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16350:23"/>they depriue of Engliſh ayre, leſt breathing it too long, they ſhould bee imbued with a deepe loue of their owne Countrey, and tranſport them in forraigne parts, to be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Popiſh Colledges and Monaſteries e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to that purpoſe, to breed in them a diſtaſte and auerſation from the preſent <hi>Church and State</hi> eſtabliſhed in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent Infants,</hi> who without crime are baniſhed their natiue ſoyle, and many of them vnder pretence of an olde <hi>Monke-tricke, Ciuiliter mortuus,</hi> robbed of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, which ſhould haue deſcended on them from their Parents. But in all of them our Eſtate is robbed, both of their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Money</hi> allotted for their ſeuerall portions.</p>
            <p>Of this kinde, ſince the laſt Seſſion of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> by the care of Magiſtrates and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, there haue beene intercepted from Tranſportation about the number of ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, whom I need not here recite by their names. But how many paſſe <hi>ſine ſtrepitu,</hi> wee know not. To the examples recounted by me in writing, I will adde one.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman of <hi>Barkſhire</hi> hauing but one onely childe, a very ingenious towardly Youth, whom he had long kept to Schoole; a <hi>Neighbour-Papiſt</hi> aſſiſted by a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> inticed away this young man, and conueyed him to a Monaſtery beyond the Seas, to the great
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16350:23"/>griefe, and almoſt heart-breaking of his ſaid Father: who beſide the loſſe of his Sonne, was thereby plunged in another miſchiefe; hee hauing purchaſed the greateſt part of his Land in his Sonnes name: and now know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what will become of the ſame, but telleth mee, hee doubts that the Prieſts will cauſe his Sonne conuey it to ſome Popiſh friend for their vſe; as they are <hi>Merchants</hi> cunning enough, and <hi>need no Broker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of their ſtratagems is, <hi>The ſealing vp of the Booke of God,</hi> and inſtead thereof fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their hands, and eyes,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Waſte paper deere ſold.</note> and hearts with idle ſuperſtitious fabulous Pamphlets. A ſtrange tyrannie and ſcarſe credible, had not this latter age produced it, that at the hearing of Confeſſions, when they begin to racke mens Conſciences by recitall of offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt Table of the Decalogue, the leading Captaine offence, which they ſet in the forefront, is muſtered foorth by asking, Whether they haue read, or ſo much as caſt their eye vpon <hi>the Scripture in a knowne tongue.</hi> Belike too inuiſible and inſenſible is that puniſhment, which they incurre of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication ipſo facto,</hi> by taking a taſte of the Scriptures by any priuate reading them. Hereto is added therfore the greateſt corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment, euen <hi>death</hi> it ſelfe. For in the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> what is more capitall, then for a man to be detected to haue had in his boſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16350:24"/>or houſe, that dangerous poyſon which wee call, <hi>The Booke of God.</hi> But in the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſend abroad, and load them with fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, chaffie, muddy Pamphlets of fabulous Miracles, wherewith they feed the courſe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks of their ghoſtly children, being indeed (though againſt S.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell) <hi>very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in vnderſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the fogge of Popery ſo ouerclouded a great part of the world; it is not ſo much to be wondred, that men groaping in the darke, ſhould take ſuch <hi>ſtones for bread</hi> But now that miſt is (God be thanked) diſpelled, <hi>per lumen Euangelij,</hi> by the light of the Goſpell; (and long may this day-light laſt, without night, without eclipſe, without cloud.) Now what a ſtupiditie is it in a Chriſtian Nation, that any of thoſe that liue within kenning of Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical truth, any that breath the ayre of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and other places where Gods true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is taught, and theſe vanities blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the blaſt and breath of Gods Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers: that any Engliſh man or woman of common diſcretion ſhould apply their eare or eye to intertaine ſuch lewd, vgly, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous fables, as are obtruded vpon them? The greater is the guiltineſſe of their <hi>ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Maſters,</hi> who profeſſing to bee <hi>guides to the blind,</hi> and ſpirituall Inſtructors of their Catholike children, dare in the face of the Sunne forge ſuch Mountebanke trumpery,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16350:24"/>and farce Bookes with them on purpoſe, <hi>ad tenendum,</hi> to hold their ſlauiſh followers in blinde dotage of falſe grounded deuotion, and <hi>ad habendum,</hi> to get money out of their purſes, for ſuch falſe ſophiſticate ware. I knowe ſome Popiſh Maſters, who make it their Rent and Reuenew, to become Brokers in this kinde. Their Fables, I haue recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuers of them, <hi>ad pudorem ſcriptorum,</hi> perhaps <hi>ad nauſeam Lectorum,</hi> to ſhame thoſe forging Writers, and I doubt to the wearying and cloying of my Readers.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble the patience of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Venerable Auditory with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citall of ſuch trumpery.
<note place="margin">A Iack Daw loued gold well, and ſo do thoſe that tell this tale. You may read likewiſe of Sparrowes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>Diſcip. Ser.</hi> 69. <hi>de Tempore.</hi> A Rauen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated for breaking of a Church-window, <hi>vid.</hi> a booke intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The life of <hi>Leo Tuſc.</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Col. p.</hi> 264. ſince no Rauen will come within a mile of that Church.</note> Yet if any one liſt to haue a taſte, let him conſider whether it bee not a profaning of Gods Ordinance, to magnifie the power of Excommunication by ſuch ridiculous inuentions as this; to wit, in their Booke of Miracles, called <hi>Pratum ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale,</hi> I find one of theſe iolly Tales, that</p>
            <p>Once vpon a time there was a Crow, or Iacke-daw had ſtollen a gold ring; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon incurring the Sentence of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, refuſed to eate, and pined away, till an Abbot abſolued the Crow, and then hee was in good liking, and iocund as before.</p>
            <p>I ſay nothing, but in the Greeke prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch vnſauory food is fit for nothing, but to be thrown out to the carrion Crowes.</p>
            <p>Another kinde of their engines may bee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16350:25"/>
               <hi>Indulgences, Cruſadoes,</hi> and <hi>Iubilees.</hi> Theſe are a kinde of Handmaids and attendants vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Romiſh auricular Confeſsion,</hi> they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed little elſe, but <hi>Abſolutions</hi> of the largeſt ſize, and dyed in the deepeſt graine. Theſe are very fruitfull hookes <hi>ad habendum,</hi> for the Papacie, which ſeldome come home vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden. But this engine worketh another way then the former: They vpon the <hi>Iudgement, Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Perſon</hi> of thoſe whom they take and hold; this vpon the <hi>Purſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Popes grand Staple Faire,
<note place="margin">Iubilee-Faire.</note> which was wont to bee once in an hundred yeares, in imitation of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and after once in fiftie yeares in imitation of the <hi>Iewes Iubilee,</hi> (which was meerly proper to thoſe people:) Now by degrees, for the better aduancing of the reuenewes of the Papall Exchequer, is multiplied to euery fiue and twentieth yeare. And now at next <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> will the wheele be come about, which grindeth good griſte for the Romane Batch. The moſt groſſe and palpable Invention for the ſqueeſing out mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the people, vnder the pretence of Deuotion, and acquitall from ſinnes, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was put vpon the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> nay <hi>Heathen</hi> world. As if there ſhould come out againe a Decree from <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar, That all the world ſhould bee taxed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2.</note> ſo packe they vp their money for <hi>Rome</hi> from all quarters. Nay, and many cannot bee content to <hi>ſend,</hi> but they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16350:25"/>will needs bee their owne Carriers: ſo ſicke are they of their money, ſo weary of reſting in quiet at home, that they are <hi>aeſtro perciti,</hi> driuen with a gad-flie to ſally ouer the <hi>Alpes,</hi> or to plough the backe of diuers Seas, to viſit the <hi>holy Fathers</hi> Iubilean pompe, to ſee him <hi>portatum humeris,</hi> to ride on Cockhorſe on mens ſhoulders, and with a golden hammer to beat open the gates of a <hi>typicall Paradiſe:</hi> where a parjet wall being to bee broken downe by the Pope,
<note place="margin">I haue heard of one who hauing gotten a piece of morter, ſold it by the way home for a good round ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to beare his charges.</note> happy is hee that can get but one crumme of the holy morter that is ſcattered. Their money they are ſure to leaue behind them, and in ſtead of it, what bring they home? A few <hi>Boxen beads</hi> ſanctified by the Popes <hi>Benediction,</hi> or <hi>Copper Meddals, Brouches, &amp;c.</hi> A worthy bargaine, for men to <hi>repueraſcere;</hi> like children to crie to goe to <hi>Bartholmew Faire,</hi> that they may bring from thence, <hi>Babies,</hi> and <hi>Rattles,</hi> and <hi>Hobbie-horſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thinke God hath ſet England in a faire large diſtance from the head Citie that <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth dominion ouer the Nations,</hi> to keepe vs from gadding ſo farre vpon trifling cauſe, but
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
                     <hi>Necquicquam Deus abſcidit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prudens Oceano diſſociabili</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Terras.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In vaine hath God by his wiſedome diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded kingdomes by the Sea. It ſeemes <hi>Sea</hi> nor <hi>Land</hi> cannot fetter ſome of our Nation from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16350:26"/>chafering in perſon at that Money-Mart, which openeth ſhortly.</p>
            <p>I know ſome who lodged in the Suburbs of this Citie of late gone thitherward, and are like to returne home, purged more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of <hi>Siluer,</hi> then of <hi>Sin.</hi> A certaine <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite,</hi> whom I could name, was within theſe few dayes preparing to packe forward, and becauſe he was loth to go emptie or vnladen out of <hi>England,</hi> eagerly inticed a yong youth (being a Scholar at a famous Schoole within the circuit of this Citie) to goe with him, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that now during the time of <hi>Iubilee, Rome</hi> was open and free for any that would come thither.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit to ſpeak ſomething of their <hi>Fantaſticke trickes,</hi> vſed to allure admiration, and credulitie of miraculous exployts. Of which cogging ſtampe,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">6. The Story of Father <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
               </note> is that Tale which one <hi>Father Laurence,</hi> a <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> now or of late about <hi>London,</hi> reporteth of himſelfe, That he in his minoritie was by Miracle tranſported to a <hi>Monasterie</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> where he continued diuers yeares, and neither himſelfe, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew his name; till there appeared vnto him as hee was at his Deuotions, <hi>Saint Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> who ſpake vnto him and ſaid, <hi>Thy name ſhall bee called for euer heereafter, Father Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence:</hi> And ſo the Saint hauing ſpoken thus, with other words vnto him, departed. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one of his <hi>fellow-Ieſuites,</hi> who liued in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16350:26"/>the Monaſtery with him, came to his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and by very inſtinct ſaluted him by the new name of <hi>Father Lawrence.</hi> Whereat this <hi>beauen chriſtned Father</hi> was much aſtoniſhed, and marueiled how this other <hi>Ieſuite</hi> knew his name. But hee preſently ſpake thus vnto <hi>F. Lawrence,</hi> The ſame Saint hath appeared vnto me alſo, and bade me goe to your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſalute you by this name. This <hi>Father Lawrence</hi> was ſhortly after by the <hi>Superiour of his Order</hi> ſent into <hi>England,</hi> where in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Saint Lawrence</hi> hee doth giue <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> and pretends to cure diſeaſes, and doe ſtrange miracles.</p>
            <p>Another like triffing tricke is that which of late hath been vſed by ſome <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> whoſe names I know better then the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> knew Father <hi>Lawrences.</hi> They vpon <hi>S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Priests Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentines.</note> 
               <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> day, chuſing ſome female <hi>Saint</hi> for their <hi>Valentine;</hi> one takes <hi>Saint Agatha,</hi> another <hi>S. Clare,</hi> another <hi>S. Lucie,</hi> another <hi>S. Catherine,</hi> another <hi>S. Cicely, &amp;c.</hi> I asked them what they meant to chuſe ſuch <hi>Va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lentines.</hi> They anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mee, that in reſpect of their <hi>Vow,</hi> they could haue no <hi>Valentine</hi> that liued here vpon earth: and in regard of their <hi>Angelicall life,</hi> they were to chuſe <hi>Valentines</hi> in heauen. I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them, whether they thought thoſe <hi>Saints</hi> knew that they had choſen them for their <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentines.</hi> Oh yes ſay they, we ſhall be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all this yeare by that <hi>Valentine</hi> wee make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16350:27"/>choice off, &amp; ſhe will intercede for vs, and to ſome of vs our <hi>Valentine</hi> doth appeare in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible bodily ſhape, telling vs what to doe all the yeare after. And for my part, I thinke as truly for ſeauen yeares after.</p>
            <p>Surely I was not very nimble of beleefe when they told me this; but ſince I haue thought that thoſe great Fathers the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> are not alwaies ſo well aduiſed as they may, when they will thruſt vpon <hi>Vniuerſitie Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtickes</hi> this and the like palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fictions, which me thinkes were groſſe enough to put vpon ſilly women and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Ruſtickes.</p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of the <hi>Maid</hi> with the glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or <hi>flaming Apron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Maid with the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Apron.</note> who diuers yeares ſince was <hi>adored</hi> rather then admired by ſome in this Citie, &amp; yet remaineth in a <hi>Nunnery</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, whither diuers repaire to her for <hi>Benediction,</hi> whoſe tricks if they were well examined, would proue little better then thoſe of the <hi>Nunne dela Annuntiada</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi> condemned for Impoſture. I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to another of that ſexe of whom I haue formerly related ſome iugling mirabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie tricks acted of late in this City, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>driuing out Deuills,</hi> who (leaſt any ſhould thinke that I haue wronged her in my narration) ſpinneth the ſame thred now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas at <hi>Saint Omers,</hi> vſually ſpitting out pinnes, and reported alſo by the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16350:27"/>to cough out flames of fire. She thus <hi>repoſſeſſed</hi> is againe to be <hi>diſpoſseſſed</hi> by the mighty force of our <hi>Father Floud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The collapſed Lady repoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Father Thunder,</hi> two potent <hi>Engliſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſts.</hi> In which action the inhabiting Deuill cryeth out at <hi>Thunders</hi> approach,
<note place="margin">Mark. 3.17.</note> as if <hi>Beaner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the ſonnes of Thunder</hi> were in preſence, and made the Deuills to tremble with the Apoſtolicall gift of <hi>miracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A more freſh and Domeſticke example then this I haue learned within theſe few dayes,
<note place="margin">A young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don now poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> concerning a <hi>certaine young woman</hi> in this Citie ſometimes a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to be vexed and <hi>poſſeſſed by a Deuill.</hi> And thereupon by the ſpirituall Maſters di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>collections of Money</hi> haue beene made as intended for her reliefe. And the better to draw on theſe <hi>Contributions,</hi> ſhee is vſually brought to their <hi>Solemne Maſſes.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few weekes to ſhew how the Deuill was vexed by thoſe Romiſh geſticulations, ſhe <hi>roared with a very loud voice at the time of the eleuation,</hi> to the wonder of many the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping admiring Spectators. She ſaith ſhe hath beene poſſeſſed with this Deuill theſe foure yeares, namely a little after ſhe turned <hi>Roman Catholicke,</hi> and that the inhabitant Deuill doth often now tempt her to goe to Church, which as her Maſters teach her <hi>is to fall into preſent damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemes this is a very <hi>hungry Deuill,</hi> which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16350:28"/>muſt bee fed ſo inſatiably with new Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, (eſpecially on great Saints dayes when there is the chiefeſt concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to thoſe their ſolemne meetings) though ſomwhat, I make no doubt, is intercepted by the Collectors. And that it is no <hi>politicke De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> ſome thinke, that choſe rather to enter into her when ſhee was a <hi>Roman Catholicke,</hi> then when ſhee was a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> And verily I thinke he is ſo <hi>gentle,</hi> that if thoſe contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (ſo often made for her) ceaſe, he will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be intreated to leaue his habitation. But I leaue the examination of this to him that ſits on our <hi>Throne,</hi> his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> who hath a happy gift in diſcouery of ſuch Impoſtures.</p>
            <p>But I forget all this while another of their Engines, very profitable and comfortable for their <hi>hauing and holding,</hi> which is, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>New Orders</hi> vpſtart in this age, fitting that vpſtart Religion. Wherein is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable a new bred and new hatched Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Ieſuiteſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7. Ieſuiteſſes.</note> firſt vndertaken by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> woman, called <hi>Miſtris Ward:</hi> which ſocietie <hi>the Holy Father</hi> though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted thereto, ſome few yeares agoe, did not then thinke fit vpon ſome important rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to allow. But now belike it is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Maſculine Ieſuitiſme</hi> will not bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerclowded, but rather ſupported by this <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſociation.</hi> And the <hi>Decree</hi> is paſſed, that it may be, and is an <hi>Order</hi> eſtabliſhed, and a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16350:28"/>Female <hi>Colledge</hi> erected for them in <hi>Naples,</hi> whither diuers of our <hi>Engliſh Ieſuited women</hi> are gone to be engraffed into that new found ſtocke. And ſure there is a ſuitable fairebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſignification in the very name of that place, it being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the new Citie, which well befits <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe new Nunnes.</p>
            <p>And as in maſculine Ieſuitiſme, there are not only profeſſed Votaries of Chaſtitie, but alſo <hi>Lay-brethren,</hi> married men, appendant to that Order; ſo in this Female inſtitution there are, and will be (no doubt) not only Virgins and Widowes, but alſo <hi>Lay ſiſters</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding ſtill in ſtate of Marriage. Of whom, if any will needs be gadding beyond the Seas, I wiſh that they may not be called home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>ad cohabitandum.</hi> Then perhaps the <hi>Men-Ieſuites</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſhall haue leſſe do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minion ouer great Families in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>For all kind of Ieſuitiſme infuſing ſuch high ſpirits, why ſhould not the <hi>Lay ſisters</hi> of that <hi>Seraphicall</hi> ſocietie thinke themſelues wiſer then their husbands, and ſpurne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> precept, which bindeth them <hi>to learne of their husbands as home,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.35.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when as the ayme and end of this <hi>new Order</hi> is (as I am well informed) that as ſome of them are to remaine retired in a <hi>Nunnery:</hi> ſo others of the more practicke ſtraine are to continue an <hi>Oeconomicall life</hi> in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16350:29"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> and partly at their owne home, partly at other houſes to imploy themſelues in inſtructing, and <hi>Catechiſing</hi> others in the Myſteries of the <hi>Romane doctrine.</hi> Which Office of catechiſing,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Ieſuiteſſes</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are very Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious and bitter againſt thoſe Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts that take the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> or defend it.</note> I thinke, will haue but a nominall difference from <hi>Preaching;</hi> and ſo we ſhall haue among them (that which they abſurdly impute to ſome in Reformed Churches) <hi>Women Preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay further out of the grounds of <hi>Ieſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Logicke</hi> (according to which, theſe Miſtriſſes muſt bee bound to Catechiſe) it will follow that Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> principle will faile, whereby the wife <hi>is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and bound by the Law to her Husband ſo long as he liueth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.2.</note> For if Ieſuiticall exaltation doth exempt a <hi>man</hi> from ſubiection to his lawfull <hi>King,</hi> why ſhall not <hi>(à paritate rationis)</hi> the imparting of this ſacred Order to a <hi>woman,</hi> exempt her from obedience to her <hi>Head the husband.</hi> And if once thoſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes get head againſt their head, there will bee no neede to ſay to any of them, <hi>Tene quod habes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, to proceed <hi>ab imperfectioribus ad perfectiora;</hi> nay, <hi>ad perfectiſſima,</hi> to the moſt exquiſite and refined incroachers, the <hi>maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Ieſuites themſelues;</hi> and to omit whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I haue formerly by penne noted concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their late inuentions and ſtratagems. I adde concerning them in generall, That in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16350:29"/>
               <hi>England</hi> they doe not onely exceed perhaps in treble proportion of number all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Prieſts, but alſo of late yeares heere are growen to that abſoluteneſs among other <hi>Romanists,</hi> that they contemned the late new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyned <hi>Biſhop of Chalcedon,</hi> and denied ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to him, nor would appeare at all vpon Citation before his <hi>Reuerence,</hi> though hee thought hee came full fraught with faculties from his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> for Iuriſdiction ouer all their <hi>Seculars</hi> and <hi>Regulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know not what Myſtery there may be in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> in giuing to diuers men oppoſite Iuriſdictions, and mutuall exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but I haue ſeene a Preſentment that was made by the Church-wardens and ſworne Officers of a Pariſh within the circuit of this Citie, about <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt, that a certaine man there named was a <hi>Ieſuite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I haue ſeene the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> againſt this man, by which he was excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.</note> and <hi>Keeper of the Popes Priuie Signet.</hi> By which Title perhaps is intended ſome tranſcendent facultie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> to that <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> for which authoritie ſome ſpeciall new Seale might be appointed and appropriated, which in ſemblance to the Engliſh phraſe might bee called, <hi>The priuie Signet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to let paſſe theſe inwards of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and view them onely in the outſide of their habit and apparell in <hi>England.</hi> I haue former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen the character of them in their coſtly and ruffianly brauery; and then I conſidered
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16350:30"/>that kind of diſguiſe as tending to the hiding them from the notice of Magiſtrates, or to their more eaſie and vnſuſpected inſinuation into all companies, to draw <hi>Proſelites</hi> to the <hi>Roman</hi> bent: but ſince I find, that it moreouer armeth them with boundleſſe libertie againſt Ciuill and Morall lawes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence is taken better opportunitie for profeſſed ſolicitation of <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi> which if they went in grauer habit, would perhaps bee checked by modeſtie.</p>
            <p>I know a vigorous <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> who being atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red like a Gallant of none of the loweſt ruffe, is ſaid to haue vſed the title of a <hi>Yorkeſhire Gentleman</hi> of ſome hundreds yearely reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new. Hee often repaired to a houſe within a Pariſh of the Suburbes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saint Giles</hi> Pariſh in the Fields.</note> where lodged a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Gueſt, to whom (notwithſtanding his Vow againſt all earthly <hi>Valentines</hi>) hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>Suitor,</hi> and promiſed her Marriage: and for the better aſſuring her that he would marry her, pretended he had gotten a <hi>Licence</hi> to that purpoſe from the <hi>Ordinary;</hi> which Licence hee ſhewed to diuers of that family, the more to worke vpon the womans credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. In fine, he got that he came for, and then this Gentleman vaniſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As this incongruous habit imboldneth them againſt the ſeuenth Commandement: ſo doth it much more againſt the ſixt, <hi>Non oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cîdes.</hi> They that by their Prieſthood ſhould
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16350:30"/>beare about them <hi>Arma tantùm ſpiritualia,</hi> change them <hi>in arma militaria,</hi> the weapons of a Souldier; nay, ſometimes of an <hi>Aſſaſine,</hi> or <hi>Cut-threat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The care of this concerneth them in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: but me it concerneth nearely, in regard of danger vndergone, and future protection, which I implore.</p>
            <p>Not aboue three moneths ſince, when I paſſed along the open ſtreet in this Citie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of the afternoone, walking in Gods peace and the Kings, after a ſlight ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation I was ſet vpon by one of that <hi>Ieſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> brood, well knowne to mee, and then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired <hi>in coloured Clothes, white Bootes, with a head of long ſhag haire, armed with a long nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Sword, viſible, &amp; inniſible, a Stilletto,</hi> a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon I trow condemned in forraine Nations, but ordinary furniture for the Yeomen of the <hi>Popes Guard</hi> heere in <hi>England,</hi> (I meane the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> as well <hi>Clerick</hi> as <hi>Laick:</hi>) With this weapon, being made ſo poinant and deadly, that it would pearce, as is thought, reaſonable good armour, hee aſſaulted me: but by Gods helpe I evaded. And for his commitment, I had the ayd of the iuſtice of this honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Citie, by the authoritie of the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the late <hi>Lord Maior,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Martin Lumbley.</note> who is by me to be acknowledged, not onely for my priuate protection vpon this danger, but in regard of the publike, for the good eſtimation and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16350:31"/>which hee hath got by the faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Office, and the good gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this honourable Citie, to haue well begun, continued, and ended the Circle of his now finiſhed yeare.</p>
            <p>And as the Poet ſpeaketh of a Tree bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring golden fruit:
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>Vno avulſo non deficit alter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aureus, &amp; ſimili frondeſcit virga metallo.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Virg. Aeneid.</hi> 6</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>One golden bough being pulled away, there buds out another of the ſame mettall. So for auſpication of his <hi>Honourable Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alderman Gore.</note> I doubt not to ſay, that hee will branch forth with the ſame fruit of care for Religion and Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Too long haue I tyred your Chriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in tracking out the by-paths of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Romiſh waies, which haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what led me out of my direct way; your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther permiſſion I will vſe modeſtly in reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">2. <hi>Part. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I come quickely.</hi>
               </note> but ſcarce touching the vpper branch of my Text, <hi>Behold I come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words repreſent vnto vs ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpectacle, as is fit for vs to ſtep out of our dores and throngingly to behold, not as a <hi>tranſitory Pageant for a day,</hi> but as poſſeſſing and imploying the moſt piercing eies of our ſoule as long as we can open them and hold forth our heads with expectation, euen all the daies of our life.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:16350:31"/>
            <p>Here haue we, firſt the <hi>Precurſor,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> a <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> going before &amp; giuing warning, <hi>Ecce, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> one is comming, who hath beene long foretold and expected:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then <hi>himſelfe that comes,</hi> Chriſt the only begotten Sonne of the Father, <hi>Venio, I come;</hi> though he ſeeme long abſent, yet will hee be euidently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>He commeth.</hi> Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> here is the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> or paſe of his comming; not leaſurely as he rode into <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> vpon a ſlow beaſt, but riding vpon a ſwift, running horſe, or rather vpon the wings of the winde, <hi>Citò, I come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ecce, Behold.]</hi> This <hi>Ecce</hi> as a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word of premonition is perfixed to all the commings of Chriſt mentioned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce Virgo pariet, Behold a Virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and bring forth a Child.</hi> Eſa. 7.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce Euangelizo vobis gaudium magnum &amp;c. Behold I bring you good tidings of great ioy which ſhall be to all people.</hi> Luk. 2.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce venit tibi Rex tuus mitis, aſino inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, &amp;c. Behold thy King commeth vnto thee meeke, and ſitting vpon an Aſſe, and a Colt the fole of an Aſſe.</hi> Mat. 21.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce venit cum nubibus, Behold he commeth with Clowds, and euery eye ſhall ſee him. &amp;c.</hi> Apoc. 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce ſto ad oſtium et pulto, Behold I ſtand at the doore and knock.</hi> Apoc. 3.20.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:16350:32"/>
            <p>Whence we learne that God hath ſet this <hi>Centinell</hi> to keepe vs watching and ready to riſe when hee ſhall call on the <hi>ſuddaine</hi> to vs. Secondly that the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Perſon</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our Attention, our Admiration, our Acceptation of ſo great and glorious a Gueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn the Baptiſts</hi> Office we know was <hi>to prepare the way of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.3.</note> to make the paths ſtraight,</hi> fit for the entertainement of the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> ſo was this <hi>Ecce</hi> to that Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and to the <hi>Angell</hi> thereof: So muſt it be to vs a call for due preparation to receiue and meete the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> to adore and obey him. And verily the <hi>way of the Lord</hi> is neuer ſufficiently <hi>prepared</hi> in vs, vnleſſe wee entertaine and obey the Doctrine of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Repent for the Kingdome of God is at hand.</hi> Without compunction for our ſinfull liues, and <hi>bringing forth fruites worthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> wee are ſtill but deafe, though this Trumpet <hi>Ecce,</hi> ſound neuer ſo loud in our eares.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Venio, I come.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The diuers <hi>commings</hi> of Chriſt are diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly ſet downe in the Scriptures foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: I will reduce them to a briefe.</p>
               <p>His firſt <hi>comming</hi> was <hi>Virtuall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Virtuall.</note>from the beginning of the world in vigour and power of Redemption, as he was <hi>agnus occiſus ab o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine mundi, a Lambe ſlaine from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16350:32"/>of the world.</hi> So <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw him as <hi>come,</hi> and <hi>his day</hi> as <hi>preſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His other <hi>Commings</hi> are <hi>Actuall.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Actuall.</note>And firſt <hi>in carne,</hi> when he came to man by aſſuming his nature, when he came <hi>adſuos,</hi> to the <hi>Iewes, and they receiued him not.</hi> This <hi>Comming</hi> was in <hi>humilitie</hi> and embaſement, <hi>in forma ſerui, in the forme of a ſeruant,</hi> to make vs free by ſuffering bondage.</p>
               <p>His <hi>comming</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was <hi>Locall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Locall.</note>both a <hi>preparatiue</hi> to his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> and a <hi>prefiguration</hi> of his <hi>exaltation. Venit Rex, thy King commeth,</hi> and the royall acclamation of <hi>Hoſanna</hi> was ſung to him: <hi>Bleſſed be he that commeth in the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is his <hi>Spirituall Comming</hi> inuiſibly,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Spirituall.</note>and into our ſoules by grace and the power of his holy Spirit, to raiſe vs from the graue of ſinne and ſpirituall death. This <hi>comming</hi> is <hi>in miſericordia,</hi> in mercy.</p>
               <p>His laſt <hi>Comming</hi> is <hi>Iudiciall</hi> in <hi>Iuſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5. Iudiciall.</note>in Maieſtie and Glory <hi>to iudge the quicke and dead;</hi> to render <hi>to euery one as his workes ſhall be;</hi> to transforme the Church <hi>Militant</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Triumphant.</hi> And this his comming is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Saint <hi>Paul,
<note place="margin">Titus. 2.</note> the glorious appearance of our great God and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And our Sauiour himſelfe foretelleth that he the <hi>ſonne of man</hi> ſhall come in a triple glory, in <hi>his owne glory, and in his Fathers,
<note place="margin">Luke. 9.26.</note> and of the holy Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16350:33"/>
               <p>Of theſe <hi>Commings,</hi> ſome are <hi>paſt,</hi> and not here intended at all, otherwiſe then by <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſition.</hi> That other which is <hi>preſent</hi> and daily, namely him comming to his choſen by mouing and changing their hearts, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing their ſpirit, by comforting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing their ſoules, is not here meant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then by <hi>analogie and application.</hi> The laſt and moſt vniuerſall comming is that which is here promiſed, <hi>Behold I come.</hi> And this is vſually called his <hi>ſecond comming,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>proper,</hi> wherein it is ſuitable to his comming by Incarnation, and ſenſible conuerſation; but much diuers from it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in <hi>Manner,</hi> that being in the depth of humiliation, this in the height of exaltation; that in reproach and infirmitie, this in beautie and glory.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the <hi>End</hi> and complement, that being to vndergoe <hi>Death,</hi> this to bring a crowne of <hi>life;</hi> that to be deſpited and ſpit on by his enemies,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> this to <hi>bruiſe</hi> his enemies like <hi>a Potters veſſell,</hi> and to make <hi>his foes his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in <hi>Time,</hi> that being in the <hi>fulneſſe of time</hi> when the vaile of <hi>Moſaicall</hi> Types and Ceremonies was to vaniſh,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> and yeeld to the ſubſtance; this <hi>future</hi> in another moſt abſolute fulneſſe of time, when the whole frame of this Earth is to be taken aſunder, and the curtaine of the Heauens to bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16350:33"/>and paſſe away like a ſcrowle.</p>
               <p>This glorious and finall comming of our Sauiour, as it is the Epilogue &amp; conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this preſent World, is by diuers handled by way of declaring the foregoing ſignes of it, and ayming at the exact time thereof. Both which I vtterly forbeare, leſt I ſhould incurre curioſitie, and offend againſt breuitie in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an houre to come, with neglect of the houre now paſt. I onely propound a briefe touch of plaine Inſtruction,
<note place="margin">This triple In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction was for breuitie omitted.</note> eaſie for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, out of a myſtery of the higheſt: which I reduce to theſe three termes, <hi>Fides, Spes, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Faith.</hi> That we muſt firmely <hi>beleeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Fides.</note> that Chriſt will come and call vs all to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A needleſſe note, ſome will ſay, this being one of the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Creed,</hi> and a maine principle of Religion. I acknowledge it, and ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> better knew, that hee had taught the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and yet in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> ſuch Atheiſme crept in, that hee was faine to ſpend a long Chapter, and inculcate many Arguments, to hold vp ſtaggering beleeuers, and refute misbeleeuers.</p>
               <p>Nay, naturall reaſon doth without Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prooue, that there muſt needs bee a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture finall Iudgement, to recompence good and euill, which in this world many times are thwarted ſo prepoſterouſly. I will men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16350:34"/>but one ground, and that touched by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> there; If there were <hi>no hope, but in this life,</hi> then pious and honeſt men were <hi>omnium miſerrimi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Curlonis malè ſit, &amp; malis bene &amp;c.</hi> Sen.</note> of all others the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. And yet ſuch is our weakneſſe, ſuch the ſtrength of <hi>Satans</hi> ſuggeſtions againſt the Truth, that wee need to haue this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation daily more ſtrongly ſetled and ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in our hearts, <hi>Veniet Chriſtus ad iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum vinos &amp; mortuos: Christ Ieſus ſhall come to iudge both the quicke and the dead.</hi> This is the ſure Anchor of our Faith, which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth and ſecureth our wauing and floating veſſell amidſt the ſtormes of the tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous warfare in this mortall life, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs from ſplitting vpon the Rockes of Deſperation, whereat many ſuffer Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Spes.</note> it ſupporteth vs by <hi>Hope,</hi> and expectation of the comfortable performance of Gods promiſes. For with ſmall ioy ſhall wee acknowledge a ſecond comming of Chriſt vnto Iudgement, if wee apprehend it onely as it is bent <hi>contra homines,</hi> to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon ſinfull men: ſo euen the <hi>Deuils beleeue</hi> it,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> and <hi>tremble</hi> at it. But wee looke for it with the expectation of <hi>Hope,</hi> and the <hi>obiect</hi> of Hope, is <hi>bonum futurum,</hi> a good and ample reward which wee are to receiue. So Saint <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 2. vpon declaration of the <hi>appearing of the grace of God which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16350:34"/>ſaluation to all men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.13.</note> adioyneth thereto our good vſe of it, <hi>Expectantes beatam illam ſpem, Looking for that bleſſed hope of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord and Sauiour.</hi> And heere in my Text, it is the inſoluble bond, which connecteth the <hi>Precept,</hi> which formerly I handled with this comfortable <hi>Motiue.</hi> For why ſhould wee ſtriue againſt the world, <hi>ad tenendum quod habemus,</hi> to holde the Faith and Sanctitie which by Gods grace we haue, vnleſſe hee who is <hi>the Authour and finiſher of this Faith</hi> would certainly come with the <hi>Crowne</hi> in his hand to reward our conſtancie. Nay, the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. reueileth to vs, that the very ſtupid creature is indued with hope of this kinde,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19.</note> as <hi>expecting the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the glorie of the Sonnes of God.</hi> And therefore in the meane time, though with griefe and groaning, yet with patience, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a ſubjugation vnto ſeruitude. How much more ſhall the Sonnes of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, beare their owne burthen patiently for a time, till the reſtauration of all things come.</p>
               <p>The third dutie hence drawen,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Charitas.</note> is our loue to God, &amp; to our brethren; which followeth vpon our deſire of this comming, and louing the ſame. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>A Crowne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe layed vp for mee, and for all that loue his comming.</hi> And ſurely, if wee loue this his comming, wee cannot loue ſinne, nor the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16350:35"/>world, nor our fleſh as it is ſinfull; and wee cannot but loue our brethren, who ſhall bee knit together with vs in one bundle, by the Angels that ſhall gather vp Gods harueſt.</p>
               <p>The laſt thing we are to conſider, is the <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leritie</hi> of this comming;
<note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Cito.</note>
                  <hi>Vento cito, I come quickly.</hi> This expectation is not long, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance is neere at hand. <hi>Venio,</hi> not <hi>veniam;</hi> not I will come, but I am <hi>now</hi> comming, <hi>I come,</hi> and that <hi>quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere the Epicure and worldling obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiect.</note> where is this <hi>citò, quickly?</hi> How quickly, when as ſo many ages haue paſſed ſince his promiſe was vttered, and yet he is not come. Of theſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> prophecieth, that <hi>there ſhall come in the laſt daies ſcoffers,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.3.</note> ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his comming?</hi> Nay, but they arme themſelues with a pretended reaſon from experience: <hi>For ſince the Fathers ſlept, all things continue as they were.</hi> Our Fathers haue runne their race, and other generations haue ſucceeded, and yet the world indures, yet no diſſolution of it by any ſuch comming of the Sonne of man to iudgement.</p>
               <p>That <hi>God may be iuſtified,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reſp.</note> and men found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> hereto we anſwere.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to the <hi>Perſons.</hi> Marke what thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectors are, <hi>Scoffers, and men walking after their owne luſts.</hi> The cloud of luſt hath darkened in them the light, not onely of religion, but alſo of reaſon; <hi>They are willingly ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:16350:35"/>
               <p>Secondly, to the <hi>matter</hi> it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note> There can be no <hi>ſlackneſſe</hi> in God, <hi>ſuch as men account ſlackneſſe.</hi> Men make a falſe reckoning of thoſe times and ſeaſons which God hath kept in his owne boſome. To Gods eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuch times can make no difference; with him <hi>a thouſand yeares are as a day, and a day as a thouſand yeares. Nouiſsimi dies</hi> are to him all the time of grace after the firſt comming of the Sonne of man in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, wee muſt interpret <hi>Iudgement,</hi> not only as <hi>generall</hi> to the whole world, but alſo as <hi>particular</hi> to euery ſingular man. In the firſt, Chriſts comming hath depended many large reuolutions of naturall time, and how long it ſhall, he only knoweth that <hi>commeth.</hi> In the ſecond acception Chriſt commeth to euery of vs <hi>Citò,</hi> very <hi>quickly</hi> in a proper ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in regard of the ſhortneſſe of their liues: For euen thoſe that liue vnto decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid age, yet paſſe away <hi>Citò, quickly.</hi> The life of man is but a <hi>ſpan long;</hi> our dayes paſſe like a <hi>Weauers Shuttle,</hi> nimbly; our life ends <hi>like a tale that is told.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, our owne luxuries fill vs full of diſeaſes, which yet more ſhorten this our ſhort day of life, and ſet our Clock forward that it ſtriketh dead before the time of our naturall circle is gone about. Nay where moderation and care is vſed for preſeruation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16350:36"/>of health; yet God for our ſinnes ſendeth common ſcourges and calamities of ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging publike diſeaſes by the diſtemper of the Aire and ſeaſons, or otherwiſe. Hereof at this preſent we feele a taſte, not only in this City, but alſo generally through this Land by ſtrange <hi>new feauers.</hi> God giue vs the grace to bee true Phyſicians to ſee the cauſe thereof in our ſelues, namely our common ſinnes which make diſeaſes ſo common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, and to apply the true cure, <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> And withall to giue him thankes that in this great and populous City, he ſpareth the fearefull Rod of the <hi>Plague</hi> in this ſickly ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, hereto I adde that meanes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſſolution whereby in moſt proper ſenſe, God may be ſaid to come <hi>Citò, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and call vs before we bee aware, vnleſſe we remaine in perpetuall actuall preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that is <hi>by ſudden vnexpected death:</hi> whether by <hi>inward</hi> vnknown and vnfelt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which ſometimes extinguiſh our Lampe in a moment, when wee thinke our ſelues in beſt health and ſtrength; or <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> by inundation of Deluge, as <hi>Noahs Floud, When men were eating and drinking, the Floud came;</hi> or by <hi>caſualtie,</hi> as by Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from Heauen, by Earthquakes, ſuch as haue ſwallowed vp euen whole Cities,
<note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> and ſome neere the place whereto my Text is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16350:36"/>written; I meane in <hi>Greece</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Aſia;</hi> or by <hi>ruine of thoſe houſes which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite for a ſhelter to vs,</hi> ſo <hi>Iobs Children</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their laſt, when a mighty winde vnioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the houſe and their bodies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beloued Chriſtians,</hi> heere remembrance both dolefull and ioyfull, biddeth me ſtand ſtill and looke neerer home. This place, but much more this time wherein I ſpeake, bids me recount the workes of God. This day wherein I ſpeake ſtandeth in center and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall ballance betweene two dayes which I muſt neuer forget. The one of publike dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, intended by men, but preuented by God; the other of danger and damage, not intended by men, but permitted and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by God. The one by common gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion yee are to celebrate in this place fiue daies hence, being the fift of our <hi>Nouember;</hi> the other is fit for me to record in my perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall thankeſgiuing, being paſt fiue daies ſince, namely the ſixe and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> I will not ſay the fift of the Roman <hi>Nouember.</hi> In both of theſe the caſe hath a <hi>Venio citò,</hi> a moſt ſodaine vnexpected diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. The one <hi>intended</hi> of our whole State repreſented in a publike ſolemne Aſſembly; the other <hi>vndergone</hi> of ſome priuate perſons in a concealed Conuention. In the one,
<note place="margin">Gunpowder Treaſon.</note> the Agents were Romiſh plotters and pioners, Antichriſtian Molewarps, working a moſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16350:37"/>prodigious and neuer paralelled Treaſon in a ſubterraneous Vault; when with one ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherous blaſt there had beene like to haue beene brought a generall deſtruction vpon <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Princes</hi> and <hi>Peeres, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders &amp; Commoners,</hi> yea <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth;</hi> neither wanted there any thing to the ripeneſſe and perfection thereof, but the laſt hand to act it. In the other were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients ſome Romiſhly ſeduced: but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that I ſhould entertaine ſo vncharitable a thought as to compare the one to the other, in intentions or affections. God ouertooke the one in their owne ſnare, and brought them to puniſhment for their barbarous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; the other gaſped their laſt in the place and act of their Deuotions.
<note place="margin">The fall of the houſe at the <hi>Blacke-Fryers,</hi> where peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed about an hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, being preſent at a Ieſuites Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> In what manner or meaſure of chaſtiſement or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment God came to theſe, when hee cut off their daies <hi>tam cito,</hi> by ſuch a ſodaine downefall, I cannot, I may not iudge: their <hi>perſons</hi> I leaue to him that ſhall come to iudge them and vs all.</p>
               <p>But as for my ſelfe, <hi>let my tongue cleaue to the roofe of my mouth,</hi> if I doe not vnceſſantly acknowledge Gods ſpeciall mercy to mee, who ſpared me from this <hi>Veni cito,</hi> as if hee had vouchſafed me a priuiledge of longer time of repentance; which ſurely in that caſe I was of corporall and ſpirituall danger, I could not expect much leſſe deſerue. I ran
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16350:37"/>with others into errors; nay, deeper then others, in reſpect of my Vocation and Profeſſion:
<note place="margin">Math. 9.13.</note> yet hee that <hi>calleth not the iuſt, but ſinners to repentance,</hi> preſerued this my life, when I was ouerwhelmed with the ruines and rubbiſh of that dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full houſe in this Citie, not farre from this place.</p>
               <p>Hee that ſaith to euery of vs, <hi>Behold, I come quickly,</hi> by the approach of corporall diſſolution, ſaith now to mee, <hi>Beholde,</hi> when I came <hi>quickly</hi> to many others round about thee, I came not then to thee by vntimely death, that that thou mayſt come to mee by timely <hi>repentance,</hi> and due <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What now remaineth for mee, but with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> to ſay from my heart, <hi>The Lord hath inclined his eare vnto mee,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 116.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I call vpon him ſo long as I liue. The ſnares of death compaſſed mee round about, and the paines of hell gate hold vpon mee. I was in miſery, and hee helped mee. I will take the cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the Name of the Lord. I will pay my vowes vnto the Lord in the ſight of his people, euen in the midſt of thee, O Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>God of Peace,</hi> who hath redeemed and ſanctified his Church, by the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16350:38"/>Couenant of his moſt precious blood, ſanctifie vs all throughout, in Soule, Body, and Spirit, that wee holding faſt that holy Faith which wee haue receiued, may with hope and ioy heare that bleſſed voyce, <hi>Behold, I come quickly:</hi> Euen ſo <hi>Lord Ieſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16350:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
